[Music]
good evening and good day everybody
welcome to episode 10 of ask a widget
we are into double digits and we are
just getting started
so today's episode is history i think
it's everyone's favorite topic
and we have a whole lot of questions
lined up very interesting questions
i've got so many questions i'll have to
do i don't know lots of shows
so to those of you whose questions i am
not able to answer today
please don't be discouraged be patient
i'm gonna do many more of these episodes
and we're gonna deal with all these
interesting questions
so today we're gonna have some very
but before i begin uh an announcement
the ask a widget show is now on
spotify so if that's what you like if
you like to listen to things instead of
watching it
then i invite you to check it out the
link is in the description below
so before we begin today's uh
discussion or question answer session
let me begin with
a story so 2000 years ago
in the year 180 or thereabouts the roman
empire had
conquered most of europe
so this is the map of the roman empire
around that time
thereabouts it conquered all almost all
of europe right
as you can see and it also conquered
parts of what is now called
germany so it is around this time that
a roman officer a roman military officer
of germanic
origin whose name was armenias
this guy rebelled against the romans
and he unified the the germanic peoples
the
various germanic tribes he was from the
cherokee tribe
so armenia's rebelled he united the
various
germanic tribes and he led them
into battle against the romans this is a
very famous battle called
the battle of teutoburg forest it
happened in the year
980 and in this battle arminius and his
alliance of germanic tribes
destroyed annihilated three roman
legions
and completely wiped out the roman uh
military
presence from the germanic regions
and this battle essentially permanently
ended
the roman imperial presence in the
germanic
lands and it precipitated the eventual
decline and
collapse of the roman empire and it
prevented the romanization of the
germanic peoples
so this is one of the most decisive
battles
in known history and
armenia is today recognizes one of the
greatest germans of all time
so that is as of today in 2021
now in 2009 the year 2009
was the 2000th anniversary of the battle
of teutoburg forest
and there was almost no celebration or
commemoration
of this event and of this great person
in germany and the reason for this
is that armenius is not part of
the history syllabus of most german
schools and colleges
so that's why they did not even know
about this great one of the greatest
germans of all time
so this illustrates why history is so
important
if you don't know your history you don't
know how great you may have been in the
past
and you don't know how great the history
of your nation and your civilization
is and that applies even more to us in
india
because all of our history has been
hidden for us and the history we are
taught
is all distorted and sanitized history
it has a certain agenda
it it serves as an instrument of
of essentially of uh social engineering
so that's why it is important for us to
learn our true history
and that's what we are doing through
these questions
sessions so with that said let me get
into
question number one this is this
anish was asking this repeatedly so here
we are anish i'm taking your question
so anish asks what are your thoughts
about this
civilization was there technology ahead
of the timeline like the chariot found
in the place
and why is there no more research done
in this place
good question sanoli was not a separate
civilization
it is an archaeological site it is an
archaeological settlement
the local tradition in this region is
that sonali was one of the villages
that lord krishna negotiated for with
the kauravas
in an attempt to prevent the mahabharata
war
and that the negotiation failed so that
is the ancient
lore the ancient tradition of this
region that sonali is one of those
ancient villages so now we have found
people stumbled across this
archaeological site
and some a little bit of archaeological
excavation has been done and we have
found evidence of a chariot we have
found evidence of rig vedic
burials of people so the rig veda
does prescribe i mean in the rig veda
there are many various forms of
various funerary practices that are uh
that are
mentioned and one of these is this
burial this form of burial
burial in so the what we find in sonali
is that
several individuals including a female
warrior have been buried in
elaborate ornate coffins with a great
deal of funerary
items and there is there is the presence
of the
war chariot and there
they have also discovered a weapon of
various forms of weaponry
including uh bronze or
copper uh swords antenna swords
which bear a striking resemblance to
certain similar swords that are found
that have been found all the way to the
west in mesopotamia
so that is what we know about sonali it
is an ancient site
very ancient about four four and a half
thousand years old or maybe more i
if i am correct so that's how
it's a very ancient site it is pro
definitely uh
around the time of the so-called
harappan era of our civilization
and it is the oldest it is the first
evidence of
chariots within india and if it's the
first it's the oldest one there may be
many many many more
examples and ancient remains of chariots
but we have not yet
uh looked for them so it's a very
significant
uh discovery it's the first time we have
found cherry it's the first time we've
found
this mode of burial and these seem to be
important
people who have been buried in this
manner including a female warrior
which tells us that females could go to
war in india they have the same status
as men
so it it throws a great deal of new
light on what we already suspected and
knew for a long time
but it gives us proof of chariots of the
equality
and and high status of women in ancient
india and much more
so it is a very significant find and we
only know a little bit about it because
the excavations that have been done they
cover only a small percentage of the
entire site
there is a whole lot more right there
that has not yet been
looked into so i hope in the future in
the coming years the archaeologist will
spend more time and then and money and
excavate the site properly
i think there could be a lot more
waiting to be discovered right there
so it's a very significant find it is
not a separate civilization
it is one of the local sites
of our ancient enormously vast
civilization
which which uh spread which was spread
in extent all the way from
the current borders of iran the
balochistan area
all the way to east of assam in manipur
all the way north to afghanistan all the
way south to sri lanka
that is the extent of indian
civilization and this is one of the
sites
that we have discovered it's a very
significant site it's a it's a
very important site it busts many myths
about
that have been propagated about india
and it has given rise to certain
controversies
as always the marxists the leftists will
try and twist
the findings to suit their agenda and
their narrative
so that's ongoing the only thing is look
look more into it
we need more excavations right there and
more truths will emerge out of the soil
of our ancient
land so that's my thoughts about sonali
currently we have very little data the
data we have is extremely interesting
and intriguing
we need more data i want the
archaeologist to get going and do their
work
go go go there excavate the place and do
what you are paid for
do what the country is paying you for so
that's about sonali
good question anish
okay next question
priti asks what about ram setu below
sinking below the sea level good
question i mean people should ask these
questions
the ram situ is now we
now we know it it's an ancient man-made
bridge it is the oldest
known example of monumental architecture
and probably the oldest example of any
kind of architecture
if you can accurately date it which has
not been done yet
but it's clearly man-made so the
question arises
if this is a bridge that connected india
and sri lanka and it was constructed by
people
by human beings as is described in the
ramayana
then why is it below the sea level today
that is a brilliant question and i wish
more people would ask this
so the answer is this
the sea levels of our planet fluctuate
they don't fluctuate from day to day
those are tides that is not not the
fluctuation i'm talking about there are
climatic
fluctuations that happen over a time
frame of thousands of years
so about 20 25 000 years ago we had
about 25 to 20 000 years ago
we had the last glacial maximum that was
the
the uh high the the
most there was the highest extent of the
last ice age so there is the time when
the ice sheets across the planet were at
their maximum
extent so that was the last glacial
maximum around 20 000 years ago
so that is when the sea levels were at
the lowest now i'm not saying ram situ
was 20 000 years old i am giving an
example
of a time when sea levels were much
below what they are today
maybe even 100 meters below where they
are today so that would definitely
connect india and sri lanka and there
was no need to build a bridge at that
time
so and then the global warming started
climate change is a reality it is a
natural process also man-made nowadays
but it has always existed so after the
last glacial maximum
the earth's temperature started warming
slowly and the sea levels rose
then again around twelve thousand nine
hundred years ago they had this
younger grass event which is most likely
a comet or meteor
meteoric meteorite uh impact in
greenland most likely
which caused a sudden burst of global
cooling
and it again rose the sea levels for
some time and then the sea levels went
went back down again so sea levels rise
and fall rise and fall based on climate
sometimes the climate is hotter
sometimes it's colder and that's why we
have these things
now we have found an ancient city called
dwarka
exactly where the mahabharata predicts
it it's under under the sea
quite a bit under the sea so it is said
that this in the mahabharata it says
that this city
sank under the under the water under the
sea because of an earthquake
so that's an under under sea structure a
an entire ancient city we also have many
temples in southern india
which are currently under the sea which
indicates that they were built they were
constructed when the sea levels were
much lower
so that is the reason why the ram setu
is currently under the sea
because it was most likely constructed
at a time when the
sea levels were lower which means it was
a time when the
climate was much colder than it is today
so when was the last time that is for
geologists and scientists to accurately
determine
but it is a very long time ago my
friends it's not in the last two
four five six thousand years it's
extremely ancient that's what it tells
us
so these are the clues that give us an
indication of the actual antiquity
of india's civilization so the ram
siddhu is
minimum 7000 years old probably much
older than that
which which would give us uh an
approximate date of the ramayana
and the ramayana post dates the rigveda
the rig veda came before the ramayana
so you can this this gives us an
indication of how ancient our
collective civilizational memory is and
our traditions are
and our culture is and our civilization
is so
great question the reason the ram setu
is under the sea level is because it was
constructed at a time
when the climate was much colder than it
is today and the sea levels were much
below what they are today because there
was much more ice
in the north and the south near the ice
caps near the poles of the earth
so that's why most of this most much of
the
water on the surface of the planet was
concentrated in ice and that's why the
sea levels were much below
and that's why it is it has not sunk
below the sea level
it was constructed at a level that is
below the present-day sea level
good question
okay if the rn invasion theory is wrong
then why do we see a significant
cultural difference between north india
and south india
excellent question these are the
questions we need to discuss
these are the questions we need to
discuss among each other openly
and frankly so that we understand the
truth
about india's civilization because there
are all these over simplifications
flying around and and being passed off
as as academic uh
facts when they are not so this is a
very good question once again
we do see differences cultural
differences so to say
between north india and south india but
you see the same sort of cultural
difference between
north between west india and east india
and north india and west india
and north india and south india and east
india
every see here's the thing india's
culture
is is very diverse
okay india has one single civilization
but it has
a great deal of an immense amount of
local diversity of culture
there are these incredible local
manifestations of the same culture
correct you have the kamakya devi temple
in
[Music]
which is uh one of the greatest temples
to the to the mother goddess
so that's in assam they worship this
this goddess kamakadevi in a certain
specific manner you have hinglaj mata
temple
in balochistan which is far to the west
it's thousands of kilometers west of
kamaka devi temple and it is the same
god as they are worshiping in a
different way
and you have similar temples in the
north and in the south and throughout
the
geography of india these are the great
temples of the oath of the great
uh female divinity of the field of the
divine feminine
right it's the same goddess that is
worshipped under different names
in different parts of india you have
this jyotir lingas which worship the
lord shiva in
all across the geography of india across
the length and breadth of india
they use different languages to worship
the lord shiva they have different
traditions different cultures
the customs may look very different and
yet they are worshiping the same
divinity
the same god that is the thing
all these so-called cultural differences
are superficial
they are cosmetic that's what that's
what meets the untrained
uneducated eye i'm not saying you are
uneducated it is that we are not taught
these things about our own culture and
civilization in our education system
and that's why we all remain uneducated
about what really matters
so that's the thing these local cultural
manifestations are manifestations of the
same culture
and same civilization in a variety of
different ways
that is the thing so yes these various
manifestations of culture in south india
are very different from
other parts of india right but these are
the same
this these are all of the same culture
the cholas
the greatest of tamil dynasty is one of
the greatest of all indian dynasties
conquered the whole of southeast asia
and what culture did they spread
across southeast asia they spread
hinduism and sanskrit
right i mean what culture is this is
there a cultural difference
the way this culture is practiced in
thailand is different the way it's
practiced in burma is different
in indonesia in the philippines in
myanmar in laos
in vietnam in cambodia it's practiced in
different ways
but it's the same culture you get it
so that's the thing it's the same
culture practiced in a variety of local
ways
and this is the same culture that was
present across eurasia
all the way westwards to ireland and
iceland the same culture
it looks so different but it's the same
underlying culture it's the same
underlying traditions
it's the same pantheon of gods given
different names and worship in different
ways
so this iron invasion theory will go
into it in detail in a future episode
we'll have a separate episode for that
only or maybe a number of episodes for
that but
this is the answer in brief that it is
the same culture and same civilization
and the most important thing we have to
remember is india is not a monoculture
the west is a monoculture that's just
one religion and one way of doing things
and in the past if you if you try to
diverge from that they would burn you
alive
or they would do various horrific things
to you
that's why they they were able to
establish
a monoculture across europe and it was
at the expense of the indigenous
native indo-european traditions right so
that
that ancient culture it survives only in
india today
and it is a very very diverse and plural
culture this
it has a plurality of manifestations but
it is
all the manifestations of the same
ancient
culture and traditions which date back
more than
10 000 years so that is the
answer to your question it's an
excellent question these are the
questions we need to discuss
more
akash asks what do you think was
happening
in north east and southern india when
the harappan civilization
was at its zenith excellent question
it's it's kind of uh tie in to the
previous question
so we have evidence of a vast urban
highly developed highly technologically
sophisticated civilization
in the sindhu region and thereabouts it
includes
madhya pradesh haryana punjab parts of
afghanistan
balochistan sindh gujarat saurashtra
even parts of maharashtra etc it is an
enormous
geographical area that has evidence of
this
incredible urban era of india's
civilization it is
greater than mesopotamia and and the
so-called holy land
and egypt and all of that put together
it's much larger than that
so it's the greatest ancient
civilization of all time
and it is described as a separate
civilization in our
textbooks and in our schools and
colleges universities it's like it's a
different civilization they were
different people
and us we are something else so they are
trying to imply that there is no
connection between the harappans
and us today and they are trying to
imply that there were different
civilizations in india
there was a harappan civilization there
was a south indian civilization there
was an eastern indian civilization
and that is the narrative that is put
forth by our academics by our professors
and teachers in our school
and college and university textbooks
this is the narrative that has been put
forth for
decades they are trying to fragment
india into little pieces
right the truth is we are now beginning
to find
evidence in southern india in a lot of
different places giladi is one of these
places
and there are many other archaeological
sites especially in
in tamil nadu and thereabouts and there
are it's just the tip of the iceberg
so we are finding evidence of ancient
settlements there that date back more
than 2000 years
now if we look more we're gonna find uh
settlements that date back to the
harappan times so just as
india is an enormous interconnected
country today
right the same way india was an enormous
interconnected civilization during the
harappan era
it's just that we have not bothered to
look into the
archaeological sites in other parts of
the country only harappa and
mohenjo-daro and their robots were
looking
and that too it's only what the british
did and after independence almost
nothing has happened
yes a few sites have been excavated so i
can
guarantee you there are thousands and
thousands of unexplored archaeological
sites
across southern india across
northeastern india
everywhere okay they have found harappan
era sites even in ladakh
so they have found places uh
interesting uh archaeological uh sites
in
killer d and thereabouts they have found
evidence of brahmi language they call it
tamil brahmi for some reason
to give a tamil connotation it's brahmi
the brahmi script developed in the
harappan region
at least that's what we know from the
data that we have so far
in the future if we find evidence that
it developed in southern india we will
accept it
it's a question of seeing the data and
the available data
and making drawing conclusions based on
that so just
because we have so little data that's
why our conclusion conclusions
are most likely currently inaccurate we
need more data we need more
archaeological excavations so i
am firmly of the opinion that the whole
of india
from the harappan sindhu region to the
east and northeast
from north in gandar etc all the way to
south tamil nadu sri lanka
it was all a vast interconnected
civilization it was just one
civilization it was not the harappan
civilization and the tamil civilization
separate things it was all the same and
future archaeology if it is done when it
is done
is going to prove this i guarantee that
india was just one
enormous interconnected landmass and
just one civilization in one culture
always going back thousands of years so
that is big what we're going to find
this is a prediction that i'm making
i don't have data right now because we
have not bothered to find the data but
this is my prediction
i am making it in the open which exposes
me to
possible uh falsifying of my prediction
that's fine
we have to take a stand so my prediction
guys is that we're gonna find evidence
of a vast interconnected civilization
all across india
which dates back to the harappan in and
even pre-harappan
times so let's wait and watch and we
will find out
okay this is a good question
please tell us about the history of one
of the longest lasting dynasties
the homs now no one has heard of the
ahms in today's world
because our textbooks our teachers don't
want to speak about
the homs the homs are one of the most
important dynasties of india
they were in power
in assam in northeastern india for
around
six centuries or thereabouts they they
first established their kingdom
in the year the year after chinese khan
died 12 28.
it has nothing to do with ching island
i'm just remembering it that way it
helps me
connect certain things so they
established
this kingdom this uh this dynasty in the
year 1228
the aham people are originally a thai
people now who are the thai people the
thai people are
essentially a people from south eastern
asia
their original homeland is south east
they were spread across thailand which
is thailand the people of thailand are
thai people just like the
ancestors of the homs so they were
originally spread the thai or thy people
in south east asia in the region of
burma thailand
present-day yunnan province of china
which is not chinese at all
etc that region and from there they
crossed
over some hills uh the hills at the
border of india and burma present the
border of india and burma
and they came into assam and they
established this wonderful
very interesting dynasty in assam the
the
word assam come from the aham people
right
so and there were hindus of course the
whole of southeast asia was hindu for a
very long time then
later it became buddhist but the homs
have always been hindu
so their culture was an interesting and
beautiful
syncretization of of the
culture of southeastern asia and of
native indian traditions and practices
and what we call hinduism today
it's a beautiful culture very
interesting syncretic culture it's a
very great dynasty
they had many great kings okay and
the most famous episode of the aha
mystery is the
multiple repulsions of the turkic
invasions of northeast india
the mughals the so-called mughals were
actually turks they tried many times to
invade
and take over the northeastern parts of
india and the homes always ripples this
there is this famous battle saraight i
think
the great the great military commander
lachit borpoken
of the hom dynasty he was one of the
great ministers and military commanders
of this dynasty
in the 16th century i think he repost
this
major turkic invasion it was a it was a
it was a naval battle on the brahmaputra
river
and he ensured that the mughals the
turks did not ever
get to infiltrate into northeastern
india
so they did a great amount i mean they
did yeoman service to the people of
northeast india
by protecting them from the advance of
the foreigners
and they were able to preserve their
culture and the sanctity of the
northeast for a very long time
so assam is the land of the
homs a wonderful culture and uh
we actually can discuss a much a lot
more about this
it is regrettable that the homs are not
covered at all
in india's history textbooks anywhere i
don't know if
assam teaches the the textbooks in assam
teach about them or not
but uh everywhere else i mean it's only
recently that people have started
hearing about the ahams there is this
wonderful author called anish gokle who
was written about there
about some of the chapters of history
so so it's good that uh this is now
coming to light and people are knowing
about these different
hitherto unknown dynasties of india
which were actually very great and
contributed so much
to this great land so that's in brief
about the homs
i hope and i would encourage everybody
to
read up more about their homes it's a
very interesting phase of our history
this is by darshana as per our vedic
culture
women and men were equally respected
although the responsibilities were
different
we know vidushi and women used to work
in ashrams used to participate in
debates
princesses etc were educated in
management some were even skilled in
warfare
were treated fairly so how come girls
were banished from education in the
medieval period
what really brought about this
gender-based split
excellent question i don't know how many
of you know this but
many of the verses of the rigveda
are written by women now show me any
religious tradition anywhere in the
world
where the holiest and the oldest of the
books
are written by women show me one
religious tradition anywhere
outside of the dharmic traditions where
women have written the holy texts
of that particular tradition you will
not find it anywhere else on this planet
so that is vedic culture that is indian
culture women always
had the utmost respect in indian society
like you say they used to go to war
there are many instances of
indian women going into war this sonali
excavation that i spoke about just a
while ago
it has unearthed the
the royal burial of a female warrior
so that is again evidence that women had
the
highest of respect and the highest of
responsibilities
and they could go to war just like men
right
so women used to do everything
everything that
that was uh appropriate
based on the female biology and anatomy
right but they used to go to war as well
so it's not like women were
prevented from doing things when it was
required and women like you said they
were in ashrams they even wrote the
hymns of the rigveda many of the
hymns of the rigveda there was this very
famous
scholar called gargi in vedic times who
could
who could essentially intellectually out
do any man
of her time and she had the highest of
respect and honor
so that is the history of women in india
when did things change
actually things changed only very
recently uh there is this
scholar called dharampal who did a
survey who did a statistical
data collection of of the data the
british themselves had collected
before they imple the they imposed the
macaulay and system
of education so they did a great vast
survey of the indian
indigenous education system and they
discovered that
boys and girls were equal they were
treated equally
both boys and girls were given education
to all
uh levels in the pre-mccollen
indigenous indian education system so
even during the british era boys and
girls were treated equally
they both got the same education and
there was no so-called caste divide or
anything or anything
everybody got an education even the
so-called what is now
classified as dalits et cetera everybody
got an education
these are colonial myths so how did this
uh there is definitely a different
treatment of
women in india in the past few hundred
years and that is a consequence
of the foreign invasions and foreign
occupation so there was a time when men
and women
they used to wear very little clothing
in india because of the climate of india
which is hot
and humid if you see ancient paintings
if you see ancient carving sculptures
everywhere anywhere in the in the
country
wherever sculptures and carvings have
survived you will find that men and
women were basically
topless they did not wear any shirt or
anything on the top
sometimes they used to cover it with a
thin cloth or something and that was
perfectly fine
there was no shame or any thing that was
the mode of dressing
of the ancient days so how did women
start wearing this
enormous sarees and covering their faces
and all that that happened
after the turkic invasions when this
foreign culture came into india
which regarded women as pieces of meat
so that's why women had to start hiding
and they had to they had to retreat
inside the household and men had to stay
outside
and go and face the world that's how
this entire so-called
apparent patriarchal customs started it
was a survival mechanism it was a
defense mechanism
there was the only way you could
preserve the dignity of your women
so that's how they started and the and
after the mughals or the turks were
defeated by the british
by sorry not by the british by the
marathas by by chatrapati shivaji
and that's what the british took
advantage of after they defeated the
marathas themselves
so the british brought in their own
twisted morality
their victorian and whatever else
morality
in the west women are treated in an
atrocious manner i mean just look at the
witch hunting and witch burning and all
that
that is present throughout the medieval
ages of europe the most popular book in
the medieval ages in europe was the
malayos maleficarum
the hammer of the witches which
prescribed different horrible ways of
torturing and killing women who were
accused of being witches
now when was a woman accused of being a
witch when she had some ancient
knowledge
some pre-christian knowledge which dated
back
to the ancient indo-european culture
so that was a way of stamping out the
ancient indigenous culture of europe
and it was a way of of putting women in
that place and that is the morality
that the british brought into india and
then they
enforce that in a variety of ways so it
is these
backward primitive foreign influences
in india that brought about the decline
of the status of women
in india's indigenous culture women
always had the highest of regard
the highest of respect and the highest
of status or the highest of status
that's what we have always seen
throughout india's history
look at the stories of the mahabharata
the ramayana the other tales the other
anecdotes all the other evidence that
comes comes forth
look at the status that maharani ayala
by hulkar had right i mean just look at
the great women of this country and the
things they have done
they will not see any woman anywhere
else in the world who would do anything
like that
so that is the status that women had in
india it is
regrettable that things changed and we
should
we should hearken back to who we truly
are
okay this is a long question what is the
real truth
of sati prata i studied in history class
that rajaram mohan roy the great great
man the great reformer
stopped the sati pratha with the help of
the british
and people like rajiv they should say
it's fake
etc so what is true what's the real
history what's the reason behind this
practice uh
this if what he says then no such
killing should happen in the country
where gods and goddesses are worshiped
equally
please spread some light on it okay
first of all
raja ram mohan roy was no saint okay he
was a british agent he was a stooge of
the british
when india's historians glorify somebody
to the high heavens
it is a sure short sign that that person
was a british agent
okay i encourage you to look up
raja ram mohan roy's true history
everything is available online google
raja ram on roy
and look up what you find look up his
own writings
there don't look up what other people
have said about him those are opinions
i would like you to read what raja ram
mohan roy himself
wrote the letters he wrote to the
british administrators and the kings
and what he was saying in those letters
he was saying that we need to educate
the indians
indians are backward they they still
worship the vedas they still study the
vedas sanskrit is a backward language we
need to educate them
we need to liberate them from the chains
of backward hinduism
etc look up raja ramon roy's own
writings and then you will know the
truth about this
stooge of the british now
what about sati pranata right so we are
told that ram mohandro
abolished this horrible barbaric
practice
we are told that lord william bentik the
great reformer viceroy of india
did an enormous favor to the people of
india by abolishing this horrible
practice of burning our women so i would
like to ask you a question my friends
and i want you to ask this question to
yourself and answer it for yourself you
don't have to answer me
answer this simple question in the
living memory
of your family only your family not the
neighbors family
in the living memory of your own family
is there any recollection
of any of your ancestors female
ancestors or
or relatives committing sati
has anybody in your family in living
memory
in the last 100 200 500 000 years has
anyone ever committed something
i have asked this question to countless
people
and the answer is always the same not in
my family
it's always somewhere else it's in the
textbooks
now who wrote these textbooks is the
british
let me answer ask you another question
we had this
horrific famines during the british
times
the british engineered famine after
famine after famine in india
because indians were great fighters and
you can't fight if you are famished
if you can't fight if you are starving
so they engineered famine after famine
in india
hundreds of millions of indians died i'm
not kidding it's not a small number i
know
it's a horrific number at conservative
estimates
at least 100 million people died you can
just add up the numbers that you will
find in history records
so if so many indians died why weren't
there millions of cases of sati
why i mean if satthi was so widespread
it was such a horrible
disease of the society why weren't there
millions of cases of sati
during all these famines that took place
i i mean is there any answer to that
here's one more one more example
one of the great queens of of recent
times halyabai hulkar
when she became a widow she wanted to
commit sati because she
she felt lost without her without her
husband
so it was an optional thing some people
would do it
and she was strongly dissuaded by her
father-in-law
the father of her husband he said do not
do it i will not allow you to take such
a step
so she listened to him and she went on
to be one of the
to become one of the greatest and
saintliest queens
of the past recent memory in india
so once again you have an example of one
individual who wants to
leave the world in this manner and she
is dissuaded
by her family member by her
father-in-law from doing it so it is the
opposite
of what people say no one was forcing
anybody to commit sati you may have
one or two random cases here and there
and those are then
spread everywhere as if it is the uh as
if it is the norm and not the exception
this atrocity literature of sati it's
called atrocity literature
it was popularized by british
missionaries
who came to india with a singular
intention to destroy indian culture and
convert everybody
to their foreign religion so to do that
they had to weaken the foundations of
india's culture and there to portray
india's culture as
barbaric and primitive and backward so
they took
they found a few here in the random
incidences
across the country a few of them and
they started
writing this atrocity literature that
indians burned their women alive when
these women became become widows and the
thing is this
in india self-immolation is an ancient
practice
it is usually an act of protest
or it is an act of penance and this is
spread throughout the dharmic world not
just in india
in the 1960s there was this famous
vietnamese monk
who burned himself alive who
self-immolated
because in order to protest the the
forcible christianization of his country
so this happened in vietnam it is a man
you will see many
instances of men in india
self-immolating in protest
or or in penance okay i can give
examples
i will not go into that right now and
such practices are
spread throughout the ancient
indo-european world so
this popular notion that indians
practice this horrible
this horrible practice it is
an invention a creation of western
missionaries
in order to malign india's culture
and in order to weaken the foundations
of india's culture and to precipitate
the spread of their religion into india
so this is an entirely a lie
and we need to educate ourselves about
what the truth really is
okay jishnu asks can you please tell us
about
vikramaditya's empire the legendary king
vikramaditya
so what we know about vikramaditya comes
from the uh era that is named after him
first of all
the vikram samwat era i think it dates
back to
57 or 27 bc or thereabouts i think 57 bc
56 or 57 bc so that is the rain
that is the the year that the vikram
somewhat era starts
it is the year in which this great king
is said to have
repulsed an invasion by the skittions
into india the shakkas
so this era was was started to
commemorate
his victory over the invading scitians
now we know very little about this great
king
the only thing we know is that we have
an entire era named after him
which is a very which is an honor that
is given to very very few people
so we have an entire era named after him
we have many future kings subsequent
kings
who took the name vikramaditya in honor
of
this great original vikramaditya and yet
our historians in india
they say that vikramaditya was a
mythical
king he's a myth he's a legend he's not
reality
now i wanted to understand this very
well when
an indian historian especially a bunch
of indian historians
say that something is a myth it means
that they are trying to hide something
very important
and very valuable so
as of now we don't have much evidence of
vikramaditya
the great king of ujjain he is believed
to have conquered
a very large kingdom it is all
regarded as myths it is all portrayed as
myth in by by india's historians and in
india's history textbooks which
most likely don't even mention him but
he was
in my opinion a very very great king of
india one of the greatest kings of the
past two three thousand years
so that's all we know about him as of
now we know that he was king in ujjain
ujjain the great ancient city was his
capital
so that's what we know about him i i
would say that we need to do
more research into this great
personality because there are so many
incredible stories about this man they
can't if there are so many stories about
some person so many ancient memories
that have been passed on from generation
to generation to generation it means
that there is
a great deal of truth to it because
after
like i said our universities were
destroyed and libraries burned the only
means of
passing down information for our
ancestors was to pass it down orally
so they faithfully dutifully passed down
all these
things that they had learned to their
children and to the descendants
generation after generation in an oral
manner
so these are very important stories we
should not
trivialize them as myths these are our
ancient
oral stories our oral histories and we
need to take them
extremely seriously and we need to look
into
the actual facts behind them and the way
to do it is to look into archaeology
and other means so i think that
vikramaditya was
definitely a real king and one of the
greatest kings of india
and i would like to wait for more data
and information about him
as and when it becomes available
priyam asks recently i read a book
called
the nine unknown men by talbot mundi
in which he talked about the secret
society formed by ashok called
men was this secret society real does it
still exist
does it hold any influence in the world
etc
well so when you have a secret society
its purpose is to remain secret
it will not make itself known so this
story has is a very persistent story
it doesn't go away maybe there is some
truth to it
we don't know was it a show who founded
this the society of nine secret men
was it somebody before him we don't know
it is
said that these are nine people nine
individuals
who hold a certain amount of expert who
old hold expertise
in a certain field a certain very
important field
and who knows certain ancient secret
knowledge
that will be useful to the country when
that and it will be revealed when the
time is right
so these are not said to be agents of
political change
they are simply preservers of ancient
and valuable knowledge so that is the
story
this if it is true if it is a real
secret society that they will
not reveal themselves they may be hidden
in plain sight
there may be people you even know but
they will never reveal themselves they
may
they may hold a great deal of knowledge
an enormous amount of knowledge
from the old days or even the new days
and maybe
when the time is right when the
situation in india is better
they may help the civilization with this
knowledge
that they have preserved and they may
not even reveal themselves and their
identities even then
so that is what i can speculate
does it really exist i don't know i hope
it does
i don't know if it has any connection
with the illuminati which is a western
thing
i think if the nine unknown men do exist
nine unknown men or women okay if it
does exist then i don't think it has any
connection with the illuminati
the illuminati is something else
entirely
this is an indian thing so maybe
i don't know maybe it does and i hope it
does
okay till when was nepal
a part of india and why did it separate
it separated in 1947. i'll tell you
let me tell you the recent history first
and then go into the
older history so in the 1950s king
tribune of nepal
met our great prime minister sri
jawaharlal nehru
and he requested the great nehruji
to kindly allow his country to
reintegrate with india
he king prithvi and prithvi narayansha
wanted to reintegrate nepal with india
because nepal belongs with india
and this is something that has been re
it is not a story i have made up
look it up online google it and you will
find the evidence
this is multi-source evidence it's not
one person who is saying it
okay so this is a matter of record
privacy
wanted wished to reintegrate nepal with
india because nepal has always belonged
with india
nepal has always been a part of india's
civilization and geography
and the very wise mr nehru denied
his request he said that you need to
stay separate from india
why he did that i can not guess his mind
was very enigmatic
so the fact that the king of nepal
wanted to come back into india tells you
that nepal has always been a part of
india it's not a separate culture it's
not a separate nation
i mean it is a separate nation today
it's not a separate culture
it's not a separate ethnicity of
people's it is nothing different
the indians in nepalese are the same
people it's the same culture
even the gorkhas are ancient worshippers
of the great saint gurak right that's
where the name gorkha comes from
so nepal has always been culturally
ethnically and historically been part of
the indian
subcontinent the great gotham buddha was
born in lumbini which is currently part
of nepal
right so some nepalese nationalists said
that he was nepalese
so let's go back into when nepal
actually emerged
as a separate political entity
so nepal the region of nepal is in the
himalayas there is a southern part
called the
region which is more which is more of
plains it is more flat
and the northern region is the uh is the
pahad region or the hills of nepal
kathmandu is in the pahad region and the
political elite today of nepal is from
the
northern region and they look down upon
the southerners and consider them to be
agents of india
so this region has always been a small a
bunch of small kingdoms
it is in the 18th century somewhere in
the 1700s
that a king called praswin aryansa did a
small bunch of conquests he unified this
territory
and he started he he founded this
kingdom
from the navara valley from which it got
the new our kingdom
name and it became nepal eventually so
this was a kingdom one of the many
kingdoms
one of the many fragmented kingdoms of
india during the turkic
and british occupations of india now
uh the british when they ruled india
they wished to use
this territory of nepal as a buffer
state between india and tibet because
tibet was
at that time coming in under chinese
influence to some extent the chinese
were trying to make claims to tibet
so the british wanted some separation
between these
activities and their
their territory that they had captured
which is india
so they did not annex nepal into the
british raj into the british empire
they allowed nepal to be nominally
outside of the british
empire and that is the genesis
of this current situation where nepal is
outside
of india okay the nepalese people
they speak indian languages either
methily or bhojpuri or or
made or various other languages of
northern india
right gorkha limbu all that is also
there definitely
it's a very interesting mix of
ethnicities all
within one umbrella so it is because the
british
refused that they decided to keep nepal
separate and not annex it
that nepal remained a separate political
entity and after independence for
for i don't know for what reason india
did not reintegrate nepal or sri lanka
into india it is all uh due to our great
statesmen mr nehru
to whom we have to thank for all these
eventualities that we are
uh seeing right now so that is
in brief about why nepal is currently
not as of now
not a part of india
koshel asks in the 1971 war why was
bangladesh
not made part of india well i would also
like to ask this question
it is a territory that has always been a
part of the indian
civilization of the indian subcontinent
and it is a territory we
conquered by military means so we had
the right to reintegrate the territory
rightfully into india by by right of
conquest
we conquered it we freed them from the
pakistani barbarians who were
massacring millions of people there they
massacred
at least minimum two million people in
seven months
right so india freed the bengals
from pakistani occupation the army the
indian army did this
and then the political leadership of
india decided that bangladesh
that this part of bengal should remain
separate from india
and today we have a situation where
these bangladeshis are very much part of
india they have infiltrated throughout
india
the border is mostly by its defect to
open they can come in any time they want
and there are millions of bangladeshis
throughout india right
so i don't understand why bangladesh was
not made part of india because they are
anyway living in india in very large
numbers
so it is the question that only the the
political leadership of that time can
answer i
it i failed to understand why bangladesh
was not made part of india
we conquered the land we freed the land
of the terrorists of the barbarians
of the murderers and yet we let it go
its own separate way
and it has this decision has been very
basically it has been very harmful for
india it has not helped india in any way
it has not had the people of bangladesh
also they have faced a great deal of
mismanagement misgovernance they were
under military rule for a very long time
etc so i failed to understand why
bangladesh was not made part of india
and this is a question that i i wonder
why people not asked much
until today so good question
advaith asks could you give us an
insight in the
into the astronomical research
undertaken in ancient india
how were they how are our ancient gurus
able to predict the shape of the earth
its distance from the sun and all that
thank you advaith
so our ancient gurus were not merely
religious gurus they were scientists
they were astronomers we had
an enormous we had a very very ancient
tradition
of astronomical observations uh let me
let me
show you an example of that one second
just briefly share an image with you
okay so take a look at this
this is something we found in kashmir
they found carvings in in kashmir in the
kashmir valley
which are about 6 000 years old and
it represents it it depicts two suns
in the sky with various constellations
drawn around them so you know exactly
where this event happened
so it seems there were two suns in the
sky about 6000 years ago
between these various constellations
so scientists at the tata institute of
fundamental research tifr
actually did some analysis of this they
looked back at the astronomical data of
what happened many thousands years ago
and they found that there was a
supernova
a dying an exploding star that exploded
around six
around 4600 bce it's called supernova
hb9
it it occurred precisely where it is
depicted
in this ancient six thousand year old
carving it tells you that indians have
been recording astronomical events
for thousands of years and india had the
most accurate ancient calendar of all
time
the indian traditional loony solar
calendar is even today more accurate
than the current
western calendar we use today january
february all that
so our calendar is was so precise
because of
thousands of years of astronomical
observations and data collection
tycho brahec got data from indian
astronomers
via jesuit priests so there was there
was a great deal of indian astronomical
data
that the jesuits stole from india
brought to europe
and his student kepler johannes kepler
used all this voluminous data
to compile the three capital kepler's
laws of motion
so all of this data this incredible
amount of ancient data came from india
and much of western science if not most
of western science
is founded on a bedrock of indian
science and astronomy
and that is something that is denied
today so indians
the ancient indian gurus were scientists
they were not just
religious gurus we had many schools of
philosophical thought
including uh atomism
uh and uh you had uh things like nia
and various other schools which were
basically scientific schools
of thought they had actual models of the
universe and
models of the world the sage kanada
was an atomist he is the first human
being known to earth
known to us who propounded the atomic
hypothesis
that everything is made up of atoms and
so on so india has a very very very old
thousands of years old scientific
tradition which is why we were able to
make so many ancient
discoveries and when the greeks came to
india during the time of chandragupta
maurya when seleucus nikita sent his
emissaries to chandragupta
these greeks recorded that indians had a
calendar called the saptarshi calendar
that dated back to 6000 something bce
that's 8008 more than 8 000 years before
today
and they had lineages of thousands of
kings
so that is our ancient historical
tradition we had an extremely precise
calendar
that took into account the precession of
the of the equinoxes and much more
it it can only be done if you have
thousands of years of
astronomical data and very astronomic
very accurate
astronomical data so that's in brief
about india's ancient scientific and
astronomical traditions
okay this is by niva deka this is a
question i get
all the time lots of you have asked this
please tell us about the ancient
education system
i think i've spoken about this before
but why not do it again
so india's ancient education system
dates back many many thousands of years
it was uh it was based
at the lowest levels it has it had lots
of hierarchical steps
levels at the lowest levels education
was
given in temples so temples were
centers of education every town every
city every village
every neighborhood had a temple and they
would have
a priest there a priest would not only
officiate in religious
functions but who was also an educator
so these
uh gurus essentially would educate the
small children of the of the locality
at the very basic fundamental level they
would be taught basic
language grammar they would be taught
the mother tongue they would be taught
sanskrit
they would be taught grammar they would
be taught basic maths and various other
basic subjects
as you grew older you would go on to a
larger temple where you would
get more advanced education the great
temples of the country the really great
ones
would provide very high level education
to those who had the intellectual
capability
to to take it and then you had
the great viharas of india where you had
religious uh
religious philosophies and traditions
that were that were taught
so you had great mahaviharas etc
especially during the buddhist times
which
also taught the vedas etc and then you
had the great universities
taksha sheela nalanda tilhara vikram
sheela udantapuri
sharda pete many many many more we have
lost track of how many universities we
have they are all in ruins today
thanks to the turkic invaders so this
university
let's take nalanda the most famous one
nalanda was destroyed when it was
when it was when india was in the
buddhist
so-called era so many of these teachers
in nalanda were buddhist
monks the last recorded teacher in
nalanda
is was an inch was a was a gentleman
called rahul shri bhadra
he was teaching a small class of about
50 students
even after the university was destroyed
and he was in his 90s at that time
so nalanda was a center of buddhist
education
and the same teachers who taught what is
now called buddhism
also taught the vedas also taught all
kinds of other subjects
so everything was taught there in these
great universities
and the only barrier to admission was
your intellect so you would have to go
through
a series of examinations and and oral
tests you would have to answer questions
from the great gurus and if you were
able to answer these
questions satisfactorily then you would
be given admission to the university
and all education was entirely free
it was all subsidized and funded by the
local kings
the entire universities were subsidized
by the kings the
there was no salary everybody lived
there the teachers the students they
were they were living quarters
all the food was provided everything was
taken care of by the
local king or emperor whoever it was so
education throughout india was
always free healthcare throughout india
was always free
that is the mark of a civilization of a
truly civilized society
education and healthcare if you have to
pay for it it means you are living in a
backward society
in india always imparted education and
healthcare
for free so that is the system of
education men
and women were all equally allowed even
foreigners were allowed
if they could pass the exams there was
no so-called
the so-called caste or class divide that
we speak about today there was a thing
everybody was allowed in the in the in
the education system
as long as they had the intellectual
capacity for that even foreigners even
greeks
came came as students skins there were
there are records of sketian students
and even chinese students so if
foreigners were allowed into this
system why wouldn't the other indians be
allowed so that
is in brief about the indian education
system it is the most
advanced system of education
the world has ever seen education itself
was invented in india
and it has been going on for thousands
of years at the lowest level
it was called the guru shisha parampara
so you would spend several years with
the guru
and that guru would teach you most of
what you needed to know especially when
you were in a certain trade if you were
if you were a warrior
then your guru would teach you the vedas
the sastras the language mathematics
and martial arts an example is drona
the uh teacher of the quran was in
pandavas
in the mahabharata especially the
kauravas isn't it
so that is so that is how old this
education system was
and it is uh it's it is regrettable that
we have replaced it with this
primitive backward colonial system that
is
currently in place today especially the
commercialization of education which is
which is extremely uh harmful to the
long-term prospects
of the country so education is all about
preparing the future generations of the
country to be great
to be good productive
citizens and to be great leaders in the
future
that is the purpose of education and
today's education system is not geared
towards that
it's just a commercial system which
churns out degrees in
exchange for cash so it is a great step
backward for india but i hope that
some at some point in time we will try
and
reform this okay my friends this is it
for
the pre-selected questions i'm going to
take some live
questions now
okay let's take a look uh
conal asks one second
can indian scientists of today learn
from vedic knowledge
on a variety of topics from metallurgy
to economics
we can learn things like philosophy and
and
real politic how to approach uh
geopolitical issues how to approach
uh state uh the administration of the
country
what kind of laws should be in effect
how to deal with various issues of
society
because social issues etc are something
that it's something that
that has always been around so all those
things we can definitely learn from
the ancient vedic knowledge and from the
arthashastra etc which is a great book
on governance
among other things as far as science
goes
we have much more scientific knowledge
and data today our science has advanced
a great deal
over the past 1000 years indian science
stopped 1000 years ago when all the
scientists and teachers were killed and
all the libraries were burned
so the information our scientists had at
that time
was what was the latest information a
thousand years before today
they did not have access to the data and
the information
that we have today they did not have
telescopes they did not have particle
accelerators
they did not have all the various
instruments we have today if they had
this information and this
this scientific uh technology they would
have
gone much further than what we have gone
today but they were all killed a
thousand years ago
and that's why indian science and
philosophy has not advanced
in the past 1000 years even one inch now
our scientists
cannot really learn anything from vedic
knowledge because vedic knowledge
was the latest and most advanced
knowledge of that time off of many
thousand years ago
what we can learn is the approach they
took
and the and they could take inspiration
from these great
great scientists and schoolers and we
can learn things like
like i said statecraft philosophy and
much more as far as science goes
we need to take inspiration from them
and
and and take it further from where we
are today and
the the interesting thing is that there
may be some
inspiration to be taken especially in
the field of quantum physics
from ancient indian philosophy because
there seems to be some sort of
relationship
there is a reason why every physicist
every quantum physicist
once they reach a certain level of
maturity they are invariably drawn
towards indian philosophy towards
vedanta etc
so there is definitely a great deal to
learn from and to draw inspiration from
in ancient indian knowledge definitely
so that's a good question
this is by weibo uh weber asks please
throw some light on the vedic rashmi
theory
i regret that i do not know anything
about this theory
uh i i'm afraid i can't answer your
question i will look it up
this theory whatever it is and i'll try
to answer it in a future episode
uh so so that's that's about it i
i have only studied science thus far as
far as the vedic
texts go i am not that that conversant
with every aspect
of it and therefore i
unfortunately fall short on knowledge on
this particular
question i will look it up and i will
try and answer it in a future question
but thank you for the question i
appreciate it
maduriya asks what's the difference
between the mughals and the delhi
sultans their origin
war tactics culture etc the culture is
the same
turks they're all turks so the delhi
which
you which you speak about it started as
a slave dynasty
the mamluk dynasty now people ask me why
do you say mom look when you talk about
the delays
the mama looks are egyptians no mom look
is a word it's an arabic word which
means
slave so their mum looks in egypt the
mom looks among the turks
so these turks who formed the delhi
sultanate they were
slaves from central asia there were
turkic slaves
who came into india as generals these
people they employed slaves as generals
if they showed
promise and and ability so these mom
looks
they invaded northern india they took
over than parts of northern india
and eventually they separated from their
original dynasty and became kings in
their own right
sultans in their own right so this gave
rise to the mamluk dynasty the slave
dynasty
balban his daughter razia
for a year or two etc so that is their
origin they were turks
the so-called mughals were also turks
right
so there is not much difference in the
ethnicity there is no difference in the
culture or the language
so there were just basically two
different waves of turkic
invaders that's what it was nothing else
let's find some more questions
so mayank asks how was our polytheistic
religion able to withstand the invasions
of monotheistic people
whereas many others such as those of the
greeks roman egyptians
could not it's probably because india's
culture is so ancient
it's probably because india is the
homeland
of the entire indo-european
bouquet of cultures and
the people of india valued their culture
to such a great extent that they were
able to withstand this barbarism for a
thousand years
which is still ongoing to some extent
right
so i think it is because the indians
valued their culture so much they were
willing to put the culture and their
their beliefs
about their lives so many indians gave
up their lives millions and millions of
indians gave up their lives
but they would not give up their culture
and you see the same thing among the
romani people today
who are wandering across europe
stateless people
marginalized operas people in so-called
progressive europe
right the romanis are forced have been
forced to change the religion
wherever they are in turkey they are
muslims in europe they are mostly
christians and yet beneath
this apparent abrahamic
culture that they have embraced they
still even today
continue their traditions their ancient
indian hindu traditions
to whatever extent they can because they
know that they value the traditions so
much
much more than their lives so that is
the reason why
why our polytheistic culture despite
being
apparently so disunited was able to
withstand this when the greeks
the romans the egyptians etc could not
withstand this
right so the greeks like i mentioned in
the previous
previous episode are a descendant of the
alina
clan of the rigvedic people so they too
brought with them a vedic and post-vedic
culture
and that's what became the greek
pantheon of gods which is the same as
the vedic pantheon with different names
so theirs is the most recent is a more
recent culture than indian culture
and that's why it probably crumbled the
romans 2 were an offshoot to
some extent of the greeks they had the
same pantheon of gods with different
names
so that they too uh crumbled it's
because their emperor constantine
decided to adopt christianity as a state
religion
and he started persecuting the people
who still
continued roman ancient roman traditions
so it's a complicated history
how it happened uh is well brought out
in a book called
the darkening age it's by catherine
nixie
i would recommend you guys look it up so
i think to
to wrap this question up indians valued
their ancient culture and tradition so
much that they
were willing to basically
gut it out they were willing to give up
their lives but they would not give up
the culture
and that's why hinduism and all the
dharmic
traditions still survive to some extent
in india today
even though even today there is a
considered concerted effort to dismantle
all this
i think it's going to still go on
surviving it will thrive again
in the future
okay let me see some more
yusinor asks who were the wander sina of
ram was it really an army of monkeys or
was it a symbolic way of calling them
what about lord hanuman well there is
something we can only speculate about
some other people have also asked me
this question
some other people have asked where
they're the near the neanderthal people
so that's an interesting speculation as
far as we know the neanderthal people
died out the neanderthals were a
separate
subspecies of humans who interbred with
us
all of us outside of africa today have
about four to six percent of neanderthal
dna
so they haven't really died out they
live on in us
our ancestors to some extent were
neanderthals
but the separate subspecies seems to
have died out about 40 or 30
000 years ago now is it possible that
some isolated pockets of neanderthals
continue to exist in some parts of india
until recently around 10 000 or so years
ago it is not impossible
we haven't found evidence of this hard
evidence archaeological evidence
it's but we also haven't looked so it is
possible that this eventuality or this
this speculation
may possibly perhaps be correct
it is not proven but it is something
that we may want to look into
and uh hanuman lauderduman was one of
their greatest warriors obviously and a
great devotee
of our lord of our king ram of lord rama
so that's what i can say about this we
don't really know what this wonders in
our words it's a very interesting uh
it's a very interesting part of our
ancient history so
and in it's surprising that nobody has
tried to investigate this i hope that uh
more
this way these these questions will be
taken up more seriously in the future
as the as the in the coming days so
great question
okay let me find some more
okay please please wait for a minute let
me find some interesting
questions
okay what is the reason for behind the
shifting of the chola dynasty
from kaveri patnam to
gangai kaunda cholapuram china is the
inventor of silk but why the silk of
kanchipuram was so famous for
from ancient times okay so i don't know
the specific reason why the chola
shifted
their capital from one place to another
these things happen from time to time
sometimes the climate changes
or sometimes there are political reasons
for this so i am not really sure why the
change of the of the capital from one
place to another happened
as far as the silk goes well
you will be told that china invented
silk
but now let me tell you something they
have discovered archaeologists have
discovered
strands of silk woven silk
in the ancient harappan cities
in the harappan civilization the arab
phase of indian civilization
and it is at least as old if not older
than the earliest evidence of chinese
silk
right so we were we were doing silk
farming on our own
completely separate from the chinese and
the harappan civilization
the harappan phase is much much much
much more older
than the chinese civilization so most
likely silk farming was actually
invented
in india the mulberry tree
which is home to the silkworm is very
much present in india
persia central asia and our people were
spread across all these regions
so it is in my opinion very likely that
silk farming
actually originated in the western
regions of india
the s region much before the chinese
ever discovered silk
maybe it spread from india to china
through the silk road
so these are all speculations but the
hard evidence says that
silk was in india it was discovered in
india at least
as long ago as the chinese discovered it
if not more
so that's an interesting factoid
rohan asks regarding the brahmastra do
you think advanced weapons used in
mahabharata
how how were they made by some chants
why doesn't it exist now
we don't have any hard scientific
evidence of brahmastra so we can only
speculate
uh did we have ancient technology in
those days
we haven't found any evidence of it thus
far so we can
what we can say as of now is that maybe
it existed how was it made unless we
find the weapon
and we can examine it we can't we can't
really say how it was made
we can't even say if it really existed
what is clear is that we have these
ideas and these memories of very
powerful weapons
from old days so unless and until we
discover some evidence
some artifacts of such powerful weapons
we cannot really make
someone like me cannot make any comments
about it because i don't have sufficient
data and it clearly doesn't exist today
today the most powerful weapons we have
are the w nuclear bombs of the americans
and the
and the tar bomba if the russians still
have it so these are nuclear weapons
that's the most powerful weaponry we
have today as far as these
brahmastra and other astras of the
mahabharata
if they did exist they have become
their knowledge has been it looks like
the knowledge has been has been lost
so that's what i can say today
whipple asks please suggest books for
ancient indian civilization i have a
separate video on my channel in which i
have done some book recommendations
about ancient india
so maybe you want to look it up there's
not there's never enough books
but you can start with some of those
books that i have mentioned
in that video so please look it up
this is a good question sorry yes this
one here
in my state there's always a clash that
tamil is older than sanskrit please tell
us the truth
here is the truth my whatever i am
telling you is based on the data that i
have
it it's based on the best knowledge that
we have as of today
and the best knowledge that we have as
of today
indicates that sanskrit may be older
than tamil
excuse me the oldest evidence that we
have of sanskrit
dates back to to around three and a half
thousand years ago
it is found surprisingly of all places
in present-day syria in the methane
kingdom so there are these tablets by
a horse master called kekuli in which he
uses sanskrit terminology
and there is a treaty between two
kingdoms in which they invoke rigvedic
gods so this is the oldest hard
inscribed evidence of sanskrit it is
clear that sanskrit is much older than
that because these are pre
these are post vedic post rigvedic
people this mithani and the other
kingdom
the hittites so sanskrit as we know
from the information that we have from
the unambiguous information that we have
it is much more than 3500 years old
maybe it's much much older than that if
the rigveda
is as old as we as we think it is at
least 8 thousand years old
then that's how old rig vedic sanskrit
is now about tamil
the oldest evidence we have found as of
today
is from sangam literature the great
sangam era of
of tamil of the tamil part of india's
civilization
so this dates back to around 500 bce
and we have found tamil inscriptions
even in egypt even in southeast asia
but the oldest that we have found thus
far the oldest date we can ascribe as of
today
is 500 bce or thereabouts now here's the
thing
in our ancient tradition one of the
sages one of the ancient rig vedic sages
was sage agastya
he dates back to the rig vedic time
which is around 8 000 years old at least
right and he is
considered to be he is worshipped as his
revered as
the father of the tamil language
so if this ancient cultural memory this
ancient civilization
memory is correct then tamil and
sanskrit are as old as each other
okay and this ancient this entire idea
of tamil being a separate civilization
and sanskrit being separate it's all
absolute nonsense there is plenty of
sanskrit in tamil
and there may be tamil words in sanskrit
as well
so we need to find out the truth behind
the antiquity of our great sage
agastya how old ago did he live and
if it is true that he is indeed the
founder of the tamil language
or the first compiler of tamil grammar
then it tells us that tamil also is
around 8 000 years old
or thereabouts so this is something that
needs to be investigated further and
with great amount of seriousness
because these are two of our of our
great classical languages
two of the greatest languages of the
entire world
so we definitely need to look into it
but this clash
of tamil versus sanskrit this is all
politically motivated
politicians are trying to create divides
between people because unless there is a
fight unless there is a divide
there will be they will not get any
votes so we need to look beyond
politics we need to look beyond
propaganda we need to ignore the lies
our academic system is telling us
and we just need to look at the evidence
and the data that we have
so that is my view about it i think that
if augustia is proven to be
one of the vedic sages and we can find
his actual age
when he actually lived then it indicates
that tamil is that much
old which will indicate it is many many
thousands of years older than what
we currently know for sure that it is
so that's in brief about this specific
question
okay let me take a couple of more
questions
i'll take some super chats
kuldeep asks why are international
scientists not acknowledging india's
contribution in great ancient technology
and ancient astronomical discoveries see
the scientists of the world
they are not concerned with history they
just do science
they learn science in school and college
and university and
post university from textbooks and
research papers and all that
and they never know what where it came
from they don't really know where the
math came from
where this ancient data came from all
that and the science we are doing today
it's all
modern science it's post-quantum world
science right
so the majority i would say 99.9 percent
of scientists
don't have any idea about the history
of science about the ancient lineage of
all these discoveries
so that is the number one reason why
scientists don't know about this
secondary secondly the science the
historians of science
are trying to deny india's contributions
most of the historians of science are
eurocentric historians
they are all in the western world how
many historians of science do you have
in india
zero as far as i know i may be
wrong i i don't know everything in the
world but as far as i know there is no
real
uh high quality historian of science
that i know of in india
and all the historians of science are
from the west and their perspective is
always eurocentric
it's sometimes quite dogmatic and
it is these historians of science who
are
actively denying india's contributions
but how long will they deny facts
the facts will speak for themselves it's
only a matter of time
yash asks are sindhes or sindhi
civilization descendants of the harapan
civilization
we are all descendants of the harappan
era
of india's civilization the harappan
phase was the specific
limited phase of india's civilization
india civilization is much older than
that
harappa mohenjo-daro is currently in
sindh it doesn't mean these are hindis
these are ancient indians after the
climate change happened after all these
rivers started drying out
after the saraswati declined and
disappeared
these people who lived in the sindhu
region migrated eastwards to various
parts
to various other parts of india so we
are all the same people our genetics are
the same you do your dna test it will be
almost the same as mine
almost the same as somebody in south or
north or east or west
so we are all the descendants of this
ancient
phase of india's civilization which is
around
five six seven thousand years old so
sindh is yes
of course they are descendants of the
harappan civilization they carry the
torch forward
and so do everybody else in india and in
afghanistan and in pakistan
etc so that's the answer my friend
let me find some more
namaste don't ancient greeks seem to
have a lot in common in terms of
mythology philosophy
architecture arts medicine etc did the
hellenic folks also study in our
universities at the time
we don't have hard evidence of it but we
know that substitions
did study in india some uh some scholars
of skit in origin
and we also know that we had this
indo-greek phase of india civilization
which lasted for about 200 years right
after
uh seleucus niketa fought with
chandragupta and then became his
father-in-law
so there was this indo-greek phase of
india's civilization where the greeks
lived they conquered these western parts
of india
they became indianized they intermingled
with the people they became indian and
greek at the same time
and many of them would have studied in
various universities for sure
fakshashila was right there in the sapta
in the region
which was for some time ruled by these
people
and we know that king milinda or
menander he made contributions to indian
stupas and universities
far to the east all the way to bihar so
i am
certain that there was a lot of greek
presence
in our ancient universities and it is
possible
that some of this some of these cultural
influence influences and scientific
knowledge etc may have flowed westwards
back into greece it is a possibility
as of now we don't have unambiguous
evidence of that
but it is a very strong possibility for
sure so yes yours
your your question is very much valid
okay let me take two more questions
this is by rohan when alexander came
into india he defeated porus and got
back
the reason is unknown is it because he
was actually scared of war
elephants which indian kings were using
as he has never faced them
the truth in my opinion from the data
and information that i have
that i have come across thus far from my
extensive reading and research
what i understand is that alexander did
not
win against porus i think he suffered a
catastrophic defeat
in the battle of the jalam
or the ravi was it that river so i
believe that alexander actually suffered
a catastrophic defeat which
led to a great injury of his which
eventually caused his death when he
limped back to babylon
there is no evidence from indian sources
of any alexander at all
indian sources don't even mention this
guy
even though they mention seleucus niketa
who was alexander's general
and who became the became alexander
successor
so indian sources extensively mentioned
seleucus niketa
but they failed to mention alexander at
all which indicates that at least to
indian historians and
indians of that time seleucus was a much
greater
king than this alexander who was not
even worthy of a single mansion
so if we look at greek accounts it looks
like he was a great conqueror he
conquered western india and then went
back
because his troops were tired but if you
look at the entirety of the picture
including india's
the indian version of events then it
becomes clear that greek sources are a
fabrication
he most likely suffered a terrible
defeat in india
and limped back injured to babylon where
he died
of his wounds sustained in battle
against
a small indian chieftain on the western
borders of india so that is my opinion
of what happened
and that gels with what marshal zhukov a
russian
military strategist and historian said
many many decades ago
he also said the same thing that
alexander most likely lost
this battle this battle in the western
region of india when he was trying to
invade
and it led to his eventual deaths
okay my friends uh
okay one last question please suggest a
good translation of arthashastra
uh if you look at my my other video
about
book recommendations it's on my channel
on this channel you will see one of the
english versions of the arthashastra so
you can look it up and you'll find the
answer over there
okay my friends it's been an hour and a
half great session
good fun answering all these questions
i'm gonna stop here today please keep
your questions coming
we're gonna have many more sessions on
history it's a fascinating topic it's a
very large topic a vast topic i know you
have many more questions i know i have
not answered many questions
i'm gonna keep doing this okay so thank
you
for being with me today tonight and i
will see you in the next
episode bye